Okay. All right. Today's דף daf is ס"ה. samech-hey. We pick up
at the bottom of ס"ד עמוד ב samech-dalet amud bet and we
are on where it
says איתמר, itmar, seven lines from the bottom. Line starts with the
word בשבת. be-Shabbos. And again we're discussing the question about to when
can one attribute bleeding to hymenal bleeding for a woman who has
had sex, actually a young girl in this case.
So let's take a look. איתמר, itmar, so it was taught: בעל
ולא מצא דם וחזר ובעל ומצא דם. baal ve-lo matza dam ve-chazar
u-baal u-matza dam.
So they had sex the first time, the man had sex with
his young wife here and there was no blood. And then the
second time there was blood. So if there's sex the first time
and hymenal, then you can assume that it's hymenal bleeding for the
next few days at least, depending on the circumstances. Let's say the
first time there was no blood, but there was the second time.
So what's the story there? How do you explain that anomaly?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: רבי חנינא אמר טמאה. Rabbi
Chanina amar tamei-ah. Yeah, for the second time it has to be
considered to be menstrual bleeding because there was no bleeding the first
time. So what else is this? רב אסי אמר טהורה. Rav Assi
amar tehorah. No, it's טהור, tahor, this also hymenal bleeding, somehow it
didn't happen the first time but it is the second time. רבי
חנינא אמר טמאה דאי איתא דדמי בתולים הוא מעיקרא הוה אתי. Rabbi
Chanina amar tamei-ah de-ee itah de-damei besulim hu me-ikara hava ati. If
this would actually, if there actually were to be hymenal bleeding, it
would have come the first time. רב אסי אמר טהורה, Rav Assi
amar tehorah, she's טהור, tahor, you can assume that this bleeding is
hymenal. So why didn't it come the first time?
דילמא כדשמואל, dilma k'de-Shmuel, maybe the first time was like what שמואל
Shmuel says. דאמר שמואל, de-amar Shmuel, we actually had an interesting statement
of שמואל Shmuel the other day about having sex on שבת Shabbos
even if it's going to continue to cause a certain amount of
hymenal bleeding, which is allowed. Here's another statement of שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר
שמואל, de-amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel says: יכולני לבעול כמה בעילות בלא דם.
yecholni liv-ol kama be'ilos belo dam. I can actually have sex a
number of times with a woman who's a virgin without it actually
leading to blood, to bleeding. Now what exactly that means, how do
you do that, never fully explained. Certainly one thing that תוספות Tosafot
points out is that it's possible to do it without actually having,
you know, full penetration, which doesn't seem like something that שמואל Shmuel
would be boasting about. But anyway, but it's possible that you could
have sex the first time, maybe it wasn't then fully penetrate, it
didn't lead to hymenal bleeding, and maybe the second time it did.
So since this woman's still a virgin, I'm still willing to attribute...
Is it the same woman?
שמואל? Shmuel? Is he talking about the same girl?
The girl, right. That's also true.
You're talking about the same young girl. Right, thank you. That was
Rivka's point throughout, yes. Yes, okay. ואידך, ve-idach, and the response back
is: שאני שמואל דרב גובריה. shani Shmuel de-rav guvrei. שמואל Shmuel is
different that he has, you know, he's particularly has a lot of
sort of ability in this area. So maybe with him that would
happen, but a normal person, if they didn't have sex the first
time, we're going to assume that that means that there's no hymenal
bleeding and therefore the second time you can no longer attribute it
to that. Okay, so that's
that. Now we go on to...
What happens if the hymenal bleeding, you have a little bit and
then it stops? Yes. So let's say you make an assumption that
it's not hymenal bleeding but then you only have that one bit.
Can you revise your assumption based on further evidence? Yeah, the גמרא
Gemara is not really doing that here. We'll see at the end
of today's דף daf that there is some other sort of evidence
that they try to bring in terms of like what color it
looks like and how relevant that is because they point out that
hymenal blood looks different than menstrual blood, but it doesn't bring in
like all the possible evidence.
At what point can you revise? I understand. When you assume something
can you...
Yeah, you know the problem here is that the גמרא Gemara to
some extent tries to sort of formalize the criteria. So to some
degree it understands what the realities are, but then it sort of
says different women are different and like yesterday it discussed is she
bleeding when she stands and not when she sits, you know, looking
at particular factors. And you would assume so then maybe you should
be able to factor in other things that aren't mentioned in the
גמרא Gemara that are equally as relevant. So it becomes a question
not only in this area but in multiple areas of הלכה halacha
about how often do we allow things to sort of be a
little bit open-ended and contextual and how much do we try to
just formalize everything. There tends to be a general inclination, not just
here but everywhere, to formalize things, just make it as a strict
law on the books, make it easy to apply, and you don't
have to sort of worry about every case by case. But sometimes
that's not the case, sometimes they actually say no, you obviously assess
the circumstances. So here it's thank God it's pretty moot because we're
not dealing... a, we're going to see the whole attitude towards hymenal
bleeding shifted, and number two, thank God we're not dealing with girls
getting married and having sex at the age of twelve. But that's
a good general question in הלכה halacha about how much... No, but
I was saying practically, as a practical question.
I'm just questioning his statement, שמואל's Shmuel יכולני. yecholni. He doesn't say
I did it. Right. It sounds like an odd... ongoing talent of
his. Right.
It does.
Yes. Or in a way, I
can do this. Right. Right. It doesn't sound like when I, you
know, right, right, when I first married my wife, I, I did
this. Right. Right.
יכולני yacholani is, yeah, yeah, I don't know, I understand, I don't
know what to say about that. Either that was just his own
assessment of his own sort of ability without any real-world evidence of
it, or look, there are other גמרות, Gemaras, I believe about שמואל,
Shmuel, but there are other גמרות Gemaras that speak about, you know,
certain rabbis that would have wives for a day when they would
go...
I know, but that's, that's,
it sounds like he wouldn't boast, right, it sounds
like,
it sounds like it fits
in that category, although I don't know specific other, you know.
But you would, you would, you skipped that.
גמרות Gemaras of rabbis what?
There's גמרות Gemaras where rabbis when they would go traveling or whatever
would marry a woman for a day or two so they would
announce before they went in the town, right, right, who would be
my
for today.
But
they wouldn't take a, you know, a young girl who's
a בתולה besulah
would they, to
marry for a day and be able to
brag about this ability?
You're right. Yeah, I don't know. I don't know. Okay. I don't
know. All right, let's go on. We have enough other things to
discuss today. אמר רב, Amar Rav, like Las Vegas.
Just like Las
Vegas.
Just like בבל. Bavel. I don't know what it is.
בוגרת נותנין לה לילה הראשון. Bogeres nosin lo layla harishon. Okay, so
the משנה Mishnah had listed, it listed all the different amount of
times based on a girl that was pre-puberty, had hit puberty, but
only did not discuss בוגרת, bogeres, which was like an older older,
you know, after twelve and a half till whenever, not in that,
you know. So how at what would be the story there? How
long could you could you attribute it? Because when it was a
girl who was a נערה, na'arah, בית שמאי Beis Shammai said just
the first act of sex and בית הלל Beis Hillel said the
whole night. Well, what if she's a בוגרת, bogeres, which could be,
you know, any degree of maturity after twelve and a half? So
רב Rav says in that case, נותנין לה לילה הראשון nosin lo
layla harishon that he does also have the first night just like
a נערה, na'arah, but then he qualifies it. והני מילי שלא ראתה.
Vehani milei shelo ra'asah. That's only if she has yet to have
her period. אבל ראתה, Aval ra'asah, a woman that's after twelve and
a half and has already had her period once, אין לה אלא
ביאת מצוה. ein la ela biah mitzvah. Are you saying this is
agreed by everybody, בית הלל? Beis Hillel?
Yeah, right. So here even בית הלל Beis Hillel would agree to
בית שמאי Beis Shammai that only the act of sex bleeding can
be attributed and not beyond that. So the גמרא Gemara says, מתיבי,
meisivei, I'll ask you on this. מעשה ונתן לה רבי ארבע לילות
מתוך שנים עשר חודש. Ma'aseh venasan lah rebbi arba leilos mitoch shenaim
asar chodesh. There was a story that רבי Rebbi allowed a woman
who had bled four times, she only had sex with her husband
four times over the course of a year since they were married,
and he said look, since our משנה Mishnah says four times, you
know, our משנה Mishnah was assuming they were having sex every night,
but it says four times, I will give you those four nights
even over the course of a year. So here's a young woman
got married, her husband was, I don't know, traveled a lot, so
they only had sex four times, each time they had sex she
bled. He said, fine, all those times you're not a נדה, niddah,
it's all hymenal bleeding because the משנה Mishnah mentioned four nights. It
said four nights consecutively, he was willing to say even over a
long period of time. Now we want to understand how old was
this girl, because if you remember in the משנה, Mishnah, according to
בית הלל, Beis Hillel, the idea of four nights only applies to
a woman who a woman, excuse me, right, so only applies to
a girl who is has hit puberty but has yet to have
had her period, okay.
Did they understand that a girl that didn't have her period yet
couldn't have children?
No, no, no, the גמרא Gemara has rejected that. That was the
story of the daughter of Caesar. The גמרא Gemara says a girl
can...
But they had, they was, there was ראשונים Rishonim for sure it
was בת שבע Batsheva they went...
Well, the גמרא Gemara assumed what's the reason they're having sex? The
גמרא Gemara assumed that a girl could become pregnant although it would
be life-risk, risking of life from the age of eleven, and assumed
that
doing it normally a pregnancy that would normally not be risking her
life would start at the age of twelve. That's what the גמרא
Gemara assumes.
I don't understand why it is allowed to have sex with somebody
before, before puberty. Right.
Well, and even after puberty, I mean it's marital sex is not
just about having kids. So the real question is not before after
puberty, I mean why even after puberty, she's twelve years old? The
question is why have sex with somebody who's not really ready
yet, you know?
Why have sex, right.
So I know that's, I mean those are the issues that you
know we've been raising throughout and particularly you know רבקה Rivka has
been highlighting and it's there, look, there it's I I don't have
a good answer. The גמרא Gemara was dealing in a society in
which those were the norms. I mean, you know, there are places
in Africa that girls get married at the age you know whatever
and having sex at the age of I don't know six or
seven.
But there are things that were the norms that the גמרא Gemara
then tells you is... Right.
But we have, I understand, but I also said that we have,
look, I'm not justifying it all, but the גמרא Gemara also doesn't
critique slavery.
But the problem is that they're still on the books and that's
why קידושי קטנה Kidushay Ketana happened a few times, it happened, I'm
going through my files now, because they are still on the books.
And what we need today is a rabbinate that will say from
now on this is against הלכה. Halacha. In society in general views
these acts as criminal, we can't be worse and more primitive than
than general society. Therefore from now on, just like they say smoking
is against
הלכה, Halacha, although some do, right. But certainly you're right, like the
whole idea about prohibiting rape or, you know, right, right. Well look,
as we were discussing
yesterday, when that story of קידושי קטנה Kidushay Ketana came out, Rav
Gedaliah Gidusha Schwartz said that if a father claims to have done
that, he's a רשע Rasha and he can't be believed. But you
said, okay, but at least you have somebody who's making fun,
but there was no general statement.
I understand, it's a problem, it's a huge problem, absolutely. I mean
at least you have a few rabbis that are trying to move
in the right direction.
Well it's not enough. We're looking to your rabbis, I am
anyway, waiting for one group to say
that this is yeah, inconsonable, right.
Just like they say smoking against הלכה, Halacha, raping children is against
הלכה. Halacha. I mean it's such a simple thing and yet it
hasn't happened yet.
And as long as you don't say that, the impression is that
this is הלכה. Halacha.
Right. And yeah, and it's not just a question of being הלכה,
Halacha, I agree, I think the problem is as you said, which
is why it's good that every time I read this of our
challenges of us getting through the דף, Daf, you challenge me because
no, because it's also a problem about the attitudes that it nurtures
and cultivates. And when it's read without critique and it's just read
as abstract halachic discussions, it's a part of the problem.
That's how I see it, as when you're non-women, specifically, you see
it as a... Right. And it was just...
And I might make a... And yeah, a little credit, I might
make a small,
I hope I would make a comment about it, but I would
not... But you're right, you're forcing me to spend more time focusing
on the problem, you are correct.
But besides that I have a different problem.
My problem is
what we've been saying today about the...
Well that's what this points as, yeah.
Okay, then we should be consistent. Right. But there's a concept that
you have, you have a concept. Right. A concept that after a
certain age and after some pressure, people move
far, far past בת מצווה. Bat Mitzvah. Right, right, right.
So if once we already have that idea, why couldn't that have
factored into the marriage laws and to say that earlier than that
is completely not tolerable? Right.
The concept that is Talmudic and... Right.
No,
that's
a very good point. And even if there's biblical evidence for the
father marrying the daughter off when she's minor, but it doesn't necessarily
mean taking it to the next stage and assuming that the marriage
was consummated when she's a minor, right? Yeah.
Right. Your step I also agree with in terms- I don't believe
in קידושי קטנה Kidushay Ketana at all, period, end of text. But
I'm bothered by the lack of consistency based on the other standards
that were obviously set, that we somehow...
Right. That the idea... I and I agree with you that I
can understand to some degree the socio-economic reasons to having to marry
off daughters that are underage because in
order to ensure they're provided for, whatever, and even to make it
a binding marriage, but that doesn't mean it has to be a
consummated marriage at that age. So yeah, I understand. I don't have
any...
And you know who talks about it?
No. Which is רבקה'ס Rivka's point. You know, no, because רמב"ם, Rambam,
not רמב"ם...
Rambam... Right. Nobody, everyone is silent. Right.
They just deal with it as, right.
Also assuming the husband's above majority age because...
No, no, no, they wouldn't be. No, husbands would have to be
over בר מצווה. Bar Mitzvah.
They
would.
In the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. No,
no. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says...
One more, yeah, one question just about this. So now that we
said all this, like so הלכה Halacha these days, you know, it's
like...
So let's wait because הלכה Halacha we'll get to if we can
get a little bit further.
So let's... But
just what we're saying is that no matter that there's no necessarily
objective view
as like this woman is really like חנינא Chanina really isn't like
a מלכא, Malka, you know, that...
Okay, so I said, hold on, we'll get to that. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, alright let's get a little further.
והני מילי שלא ראתה, Ve-hani milei she-lo ra'ata, when is that that
it's four nights like a נערה Na'ara when she has not yet
had her period? אבל ראתה, Aval ra'ata, a young woman who... had
a girl who has had her period and now she's twelve and
a half, she's a בוגרת, Bogeres, אין לה בעילת מצוה, Ein lah
b'ilah mitzvah, then everybody would agree that she only after the first
act of sex any bleeding would have to be considered hymenal bleeding.
So the גמרא Gemara says ורמינהו, U'reminhu, no more, ורמינהו U'reminhu I'll
ask you, מעשה ונתן לה רבי ארבע לילות מתוך שנים עשר חודש.
Ma'aseh venatan lah Rebbi arba leilos mitoch shenim asar chodesh. Rebbi gave
a girl four nights over twelve months, not just four consecutive nights,
that the bleeding was not a problem. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's
the case that it was over twelve months? אילימא דיהב לה כולה
בימי קטנות, Ilima deyahav lah kulla bimei katnus, if he gave her,
it was a year while she was still a קטנה Ketannah under
the age of twelve? So then, עד שתחיה המכה תנן, Ad shetichyeh
hamakkah tenan, then it's not about four nights. If it's under twelve,
because she's still pre-puberty,
we give her much longer to assume that the bleeding is hymenal
bleeding until there's evidence that the wound has healed. אלא, Ella, so
what's the case where we know that there's a four days that
we, four nights we give a girl that we give her to
assume it's hymenal bleeding? דיהב לה כולה בימי נערות. Deyahav lah kulla
bimei naarus. The משנה Mishnah said when she's a נערה, Na'arah, we
give her, that, that's when she has four nights. And here Rebbi
said even if those four nights are spread over a long period
of
time, from the time she hits בת מצוה. Bas Mitzvah. So נערה,
Na'arah, שנים עשר חודש מי איכא? Shenim asar chodesh mi ika? You
don't have that over a month, over a year? והאמר שמואל, V'ha'amar
Shmuel, Shmuel says, again, Shmuel's been quoted a lot, אין בין נערות
לבגרות אלא ששה חדשים בלבד. Ein bein naarus l'vagruss ella shisha chodashim
bilvad. From the time a girl hits בת מצוה, Bas Mitzvah, she's
a נערה Na'arah till she's a בוגרת, Bogeres, considered to be a
fully mature adult, is six months. So וכי תימא בציר מהכי וליכא,
V'chi teima batzir mehachi u'leika, maybe it's no fewer than six months?
Thank you. הא טפי
איכא, Ha tfei ika, maybe the period of till she's a בוגרת
Bogeres could be more than six months depending on her individual degree
of maturation? So if that's true, הבלבד קאמר, Ha bilvad ka'amar, that's
only six months, exactly six months. So it's usually a girl who's
נערה, Na'arah, בת מצוה Bas Mitzvah that we give four nights, which
would fit this story, but that period only lasts six months. So
the גמרא Gemara says אלא דיהב לה שתים בימי קטנות ושתים בימי
נערות. Ella deyahav lah shtayim bimei katnus ushtayim bimei naarus. All right,
so maybe it, you know, it extended over two periods. It started
as a קטנה Ketannah that she got married and she bled, let's
say they had sex let's say twice and she bled twice, and
then she bled two times as a נערה. Na'arah. So in the
end because it ended as a נערה, Na'arah, you only, she was
limited to four times and he gave her those four times over
that year. So that's the scenario. So the גמרא Gemara says הבעא
מיניה רבי חנינא בר שלמיא מהו מרב. Haba minyah Rebbi Chanina bar
Shalamya mahu me'Rav. Rebbi Chanina bar Shalamya asked Rav, הגיע זמן ולא
ניסת תחת בעלה מהו? Higia zman velo nisset tachas ba'alah mahu? Let's
say exactly this scenario happened. She gets married pre-בת מצוה Bas Mitzvah
before she's puberty, it's not הגיע זמן ולא ניסת, Higia zman velo
nisset, where in that case if she's having sex it is
עד שתחיה המכה, Ad shetichyeh hamakkah, there's no limit of four days.
And then she hits puberty while she's married. So and where normally
we say the limit is four days, how, what is her, you
know, how much time do you give her in that case to
assume it's hymenal bleeding? אמר ליה, Amar leih, and he said back,
כל ביאה שאתה בועל אינה אלא אחת. Kol biah she'attah bo'el einah
ella achas. All the acts of sex that he is having, interesting
that it's sort of framed in the second person, all the acts
of sex that you are having only count as one, meaning all
the time they've had sex when she was a קטנה Ketannah again,
I understand I deeply problematic emphasizing multiple times of sex as a
קטנה Ketannah but because she's a קטנה Ketannah there was no limit,
four days, X number of days, it was very open-ended until the
wound heals. So those only count as one, and now she's a
נערה, Na'arah, and now three more times, three more times of bleeding
is the limit till you stop, till you consider it to be
no longer bleeding hymenal. והשאר משלימין לה ארבע לילות. V'hashar mashlimin lah
arba leilos. And the rest complete up to four. So do you
understand? The scenario is is that prior to her becoming בת מצוה
Bas Mitzvah it was open-ended when you could consider hymenal
bleeding.
Once she hits בת מצוה Bas Mitzvah it's four nights of, you
assume hymenal, after that, no. So let's say it went from pre-בת
מצוה Bas Mitzvah to בת מצוה. Bas Mitzvah. So how do you
do the counting? Now that she's post-בת מצוה Bas Mitzvah you only
have four, but there was many times pre. So anytime pre only
counts as one, and now you have three more times of having
bleeding and sex and bleeding after בת מצוה Bas Mitzvah and that
gets four. So this still doesn't work with the story of Rebbi,
because Rebbi said over the course of a year four times. If
there were multiple times pre-בת מצוה, Bas Mitzvah, then that wouldn't count,
then they wouldn't count towards more than one, right? If it was
two pre and two post, that only adds up to three, because
anything pre-בת מצוה Bas Mitzvah only counts as one. So the גמרא
Gemara says yeah,
we're seeing all along עד שתחיה המכה, Ad shetichyeh hamakkah, which has
nothing to do, like if she, if she שלא הגיע זמנה, shelo
higia zmanah, עד שתחיה המכה, Ad shetichyeh hamakkah, which to me would
seem that like you don't have those four days.
I know, but then you went into a period where she's post-בת
מצוה. Bas Mitzvah. And it's not that the wound at a younger
age causes more bleeding. The reason that there's less time, there's more
time at a young age is because you're not, there's less to
be concerned with real menstrual bleeding. So the wound is the same,
so therefore once she moves into a time where she's older and
there's a greater likelihood of menstrual bleeding, you
can't.
before okay,
so we're assuming that that criteria has not been satisfied. It has
not been the criteria of תליית המכה tliyas hamaka as defined earlier.
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא דהב לה. ella d'yahav la. So
obviously what we have to say is, if we want to limit
it to four and doing multiple times as a קטנה ktana will
not, you know, doesn't count as multiple, the only possible scenario is
דהב לה אחת בימי קטנות ושתיים בימי נערות ואחת בימי בגרות. d'yahav
la achas b'yemei katnus v'shtayim b'yemei naarus v'achas b'yemei bagrus.
So it has to be one as a קטנה, ktana, two as
a נערה, naara, and one as a בוגרת. bogeres. Why? Because we're
assuming that it's evenly spaced. Evenly spaced is three months between each
one. Now תוספות Tosafot actually points out it's not because since you're
talking about four times having sex over twelve months, evenly spaced actually
means how much between each act? How many gaps? Not three months
but four months. If it's four points, there's three gaps. Okay, so
there's big תוספות Tosafot figuring out why the גמרא Gemara assumes the
gaps are three months and not four months, but we're not going
to worry about that at this stage. The גמרא Gemara assumes that
the gaps are three months. So the גמרא Gemara says look, the
period of נערות naarus is six months. Okay, so we have to
assume one time, this time we had sex four times over twelve
months, and it's
one time as a קטנה, ktana, two times as a נערה naara
because that will span six months, and because that period is only
six months, and one time as a בוגרת. bogeres. Okay, and that
would be the scenario where רבי Rebbi said, ah, four times spread
out count as, those are your four times. But the question is,
how come when she moves into the בוגרת bogeres period she still
is on the four time count? That should be a period which
has even less time. So let's take a look. Yes, questions on
the
periods?
Yeah, the נערה naara and the בוגרת. bogeres. Yeah, pre-בת מצוה bas
mitzvah is a קטנה, ktana, hitting בת מצוה bas mitzvah is a
נערה, naara, and then בוגרת bogeres is sometimes, you know, is basically
six months after she's a נערה. naara.
Having a period every,
well, that's not, that's not clear when whether she's, she's
able to get her period from the beginning of the time she's
a קטנה. ktana. Whether she actually had her period is not clear.
Maybe she had it already as a קטנה, ktana, maybe only as
a בוגרת. bogeres. It's not clear when she had it.
But she is one at the נערה? naara? Yeah.
Okay, that's הגיע זמנה לראות. higia zmana liros. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא דהב לה אחת בימי קטנות, ella d'yahav la achas b'yemei
katnus, one as a minor, ושתיים בימי נערות, v'shtayim b'yemei naarus, two
as a נערה, naara, ואחת בימי בגרות, v'achas b'yemei bagrus, and one
as a בוגרת. bogeres. So and that's where you had four nights
and he gave it to her even over the course of a
year that it's not a problem, she was bleeding, it was hymen
blood. אי אמרת בשלמא בוגרת בעלמא יהבינן לה טפי, ei amart bishlama
bogeres b'alma yahavinan lah tfei, if you say that a normal בוגרת
bogeres we give more than just one night, because here we're saying
that a בוגרת, bogeres, right, the same what was a בוגרת bogeres
who actually had had her period only gets one night. So if
a normal בוגרת bogeres gets more than a night, even if it's
just two nights you would give a בוגרת, bogeres, then we understand
why the idea is of adding up the four. כי היכי דהני
קטנות בימי נערות למבצר חדא, ki heichi d'hanei katnus b'yemei naarus l'mivtzar
chada, the same way in the previous scenario if they had sex
multiple times as a קטנה ktana it would count as one towards
the four times as a נערה. naara. So it subtracts one. הני
נמי נערות לבגרות, hanei nami naarus l'bagrus, so let's say they had
sex three, two to three times as a נערה naara and as
a בוגרת, bogeres, let's say you were it was allowed two nights,
then you could say okay, if he had sex multiple times as
a קטנה ktana and a נערה, naara, now you're a בוגרת, bogeres,
instead of two nights you get one night למבצר חדא, l'mivtzar chada,
that would make sense. So basically the point is if this is
spanning from being a קטנה ktana to a בוגרת, bogeres, what is
normally the allowance for a בוגרת? bogeres? If the allowance is more
than one night, then we can say okay, because there was sex
a few times prior to בגרות, bagrus, when you hit בגרות bagrus
you had one night less, that would make sense. אלא אי אמרת
בוגרת בעלמא לא יהבינן לה טפי, ella ei amart bogeres b'alma lo
yahavinan lah tfei, if רב Rav is saying that a normal בוגרת
bogeres always only gets one night, ולא יהבינן לה אלא בעילת מצוה
ותו לא, v'lo yahavinan lah ella beilas mitzvah v'su lo, and not
even one night? If he's saying that they only get the act
of sex, not even the whole night,
so what does this mean that רבי Rebbi gave this girl four
nights over the course of a year? Right, it's not even about
four. Once you hit בגרות, bagrus, that alone says only one night,
and not even one night, just the act of sex. So what's
the idea? How do you get a scenario of adding up four
nights over the course of the year? That's the גמרא's Gemara's question.
Of course רב Rav himself said that it was only once she
had her period, I don't know how we know she had her
period. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara has an easier answer. The גמרא Gemara
says לעולם דהב לה אחת בימי קטנות וג' בימי נערות. le'olam d'yahav
la achas b'yemei katnus v'gimel b'yemei naarus. Forget it, she's not a
בוגרת. bogeres.
Why can't you just say that she bled four times in the
year? Half of the year passed
from the time she was a קטנה. ktana. She was a קטנה,
ktana, she had sex once. Six months later, no sex then. Six
months later she became a נערה naara and then they had sex
three times as a נערה. naara. Okay. מי סברת כל תלתא ירחי
חדא עונה? mi savras kol tlata yarchei chada ona? What makes you
think that we're making a gap between each act of sex of
three months? No. כל תרי ירחי חדא עונה. kol trei yarchei chada
ona. It was a gap of two months between each act of
sex, so forget בגרות. bagrus. We're working in נערה, na'ara, that a
נערה na'ara has four nights. רבי Rebbi said, I will give those
four nights of assumed dead time, no bleeding, even if they're non-consecutive,
even spread out over a year. You have a question, how do
you get a year as a נערה? na'ara? נערה na'ara is normally
six months. The answer is fine. One act of sex as a
קטנה, ketana, and then a few months later, three acts, six months
later, three acts of sex during the six-month period as a נערה.
na'ara. And therefore, that was the four times he gave her over
the course of a year. Six months of the year was prior
to being a נערה, na'ara, six months during נערה. na'ara. So that
was a whole long attempt to try to discuss רב's Rav's position.
But the focus now, but it's biologically absurd, yes,
to believe that within a year period of
time, yes, this hymenal bleeding over the course of a year?
Even if they're not having sex, and even if, let's say, it
was not
full penetration? Why can't it be? I mean, there definitely cases I
know that a couple soon after they get married, the first time,
you know, if they're inexperienced or whatever, the first
time, there'll be some bleeding, and then there'll still be bleeding maybe
the next two or three times because the hymen still hasn't fully,
you know, torn. The opening hasn't opened up enough.
Over the course of a year?
Well, I ask you, I mean, what's happening over the course of
a year? It just falls away, I mean not falls away, it
opens more by itself?
If it happens over the year, it's the physical, there's a little
puncture, yes, and it will
grow over the course of a year, like it will heal. No,
heal is the opposite, then there would be more reason for bleeding.
No, it doesn't heal.
But will it open by itself?
Yes, because you move your body.
So if you walk or you stretch or you run or...
I understand, but there's always a little hole there anyway because that's
how the blood gets out before while a woman is still a
virgin. And even when we live active lives, some women, the hymen
tears before they're married because of their active lives, but for some
it doesn't. I mean, is that, is that obvious to you that
even with some puncture it will necessarily open by itself over the
course of a year?
It's not logical to assume that over what is it, five years
period of time, yes, from childhood to puberty to...
Alright, I'm just saying I don't, to me it doesn't
seem, I mean you obviously know, it's a slow process of a
puncture, where the more logical explanation is
that she's getting her period.
I
understand, but the גמרא Gemara is also dealing with a case where
is dealing with a case where there's no other evidence that she's
had her period yet. She's only bleeding during the acts of sex,
she's not bleeding between that period. So this is a pre-puberty girl
who has never had evidence of yet having had her period.
She bled four times then, and the fifth time
we're
going to assume that that already might be her period, even though...
I don't know, to me it doesn't seem absurd, she has yet
to have evidence of having had her period, and why, you know,
is it crazy that the hymen hasn't completely torn?
Over a period of a year?
Again, I don't know why it's so obvious that it'll tear by
itself. I mean, maybe, but... I understand. Alright, anyway. So let's take
a look. Now we continue. Now we move on because we are
moving into a zone where we start talking about אילונית Aylonis stuff
today and how a lot of this becomes moot. So let's take
a look. מנימין מסכסניא, Menimin mi-Sakhsanya, so מנימין Menimin from this place
סכסניא, Sakhsanya, הוה שקיב ואזיל לאתריה דשמואל, hava shakiv ve-azil le-asrei de-Shmuel,
was going on a little trip to
שמואל's Shmuel's place. וסבר למיעבד עובדא כוותיה דרב, ve-savar le-me’avad uvda kevasei
de-Rav, and he wanted to rule like רב. Rav. רב Rav says
that a בוגרת bogeres has the first night, meaning multiple times of
sex the first night, assuming that she has yet to have had
her period. If she's had her period in the past, then they
could only attribute it for the first act of sex. So he
wanted to rule like רב Rav that somebody apparently asked him a
שאלה, shaila, and he wanted to rule like רב Rav that the
first night is fine even multiple times even as a בוגרת. bogeres.
But then he said, אפילו ראתה, afilu ra’ata, right, אפילו ראתה, afilu
ra’ata,
even if she's already had her period once before. Where we saw
before that רב Rav qualified his statement and said, no, once she's
had her period they only have the first act. So what happened?
אמר לא פליג רב בין ראתה לבין לא ראתה. amar lo palig
Rav bein ra’ata levein lo ra’ata.
He claimed רב Rav didn't distinguish between whether she's had her period
or not, even a בוגרת bogeres has the entire first night. A
בוגרת bogeres is like a נערה na'ara in that regard, she has
the first night regardless. בין ראתה לבין לא ראתה. bein ra’ata levein
lo ra’ata. קדים שכיב באורחא, kadim shakiv be-orcha,
but what happened is he died on his trip. Okay. So before
he had a chance to פסק pasken that way, somehow people knew
that he was going to פסק pasken that way, before he had
a chance to פסק pasken that way he dropped dead in his
journey. So I don't know how they knew what he was intending
to פסק. pasken. קרא שמואל עליה דרב, kara Shmuel alei de-Rav, so
שמואל Shmuel said regarding רב, Rav, לא יאונה לצדיק כל און. lo
ye’une l’tzaddik kol aven.
So to the righteous person will not occur any terrible thing. Meaning
רב Rav was protected from this terrible thing of this person ruling
like him in an overly lenient way and misunderstanding what רב Rav
ruled by the person dropping dead. So see how God was looking
out for רב, Rav, He prevented. any רב Rav from suffering, he
killed this guy from preventing רב Rav from suffering this person's wrong
ruling. Okay, so make of that what you will. And now we
have another statement which I don't know other than that it quotes
רב. Rav. I don't know what it's doing here. אמר רב חיננא
בר שמייא משמיה דרב, Amar Rav Chinana bar Shmaya mishmei d'Rav,
maybe the גמרא Gemara just didn't want to end with that little
story, so we have another little אגדית aggadic line. כיון שנתקו שיניו
של אדם, Keivan shenitku shinav shel adam,
once a person's teeth have been loosened, fall out, whatever, meaning a
person's growing old, נתמעטו מזונותיו, nismatu mezonosav, his
his
sustenance becomes less, meaning he's not able to make as much money.
The מהרש"א Maharsha says the point is that you should make a
lot of money when you're young so you don't so you'll have
what to live off when you get older. So how do you
know this? שנאמר, Shene'emar, what? Go to Yeshiva Day School.
Yeah, I guess.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, as the verse says, אני נתתי לכם נקיון שנים, Ani
natati lachem nikayon shinayim,
I have given you cleanliness of teeth, but here it's sort of
playing I think a word of נקיון nikayon and נתקו nitku were
like לנתק, l'nateik, a falling
out of teeth, בכל עריכם, b'chol areichem, in all of your cities,
וחוסר לחם בכל מקומותיכם, v'choser lechem b'chol mekomoteichem,
and a lack of bread. So presumably it means your teeth are
clean because you're not eating anything, but here the play on words
is is that your teeth are falling out and therefore you're not
you don't have food, you're not you're not able to make a
lot of money. Make money while you are young and you can
live off of it. What that has to do with this I
have no idea, other than that it distracts us a little bit
from that previous story of the person dying before he could rule
incorrectly like רב. Rav.
And that
might be appropriate today's current economic situation.
Well, that might be, yeah. It's a little bit easier on on
רב Rav I think if I understand right at the end of
in terms of that that the person מנימין Minyamin wasn't didn't didn't.
Oh, I see. Not that the person, no, that's a good point.
his own misruling. That's a good point. I just noticed that. A
little better. Meaning it's not that the person he would have ruled
for would have been hurt by this misruling, but that this person
was saved from having
misinterpreted רב Rav in a practical way. All right, yes.
I meant to this I read an article yesterday about the baby
boomers and what percentage actually have enough savings for their for their
later years.
Right, right, no, that's obviously very practical that issue. Yep. Okay, now
back to this issue about how much depending on how old the
girl is. ראתה בעודה בבית אביה, Ra'asa b'odo b'veis aviya, if she
had her period when she was in her father's house and she's
still a קטנה, ketanah, then you have the debate of בית הלל
Beis Hillel and בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. Still a נערה, na'arah, debate
of בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. בית שמאי
Beis Shammai says the first act and בית הלל Beis Hillel says
the whole night. תנו רבנן. Tenu rabanan. ראתה בעודה בבית אביה, Ra'asa
b'odo b'veis aviya, she saw when she was still in her father's
house, בית הלל אומרים כל הלילה שלה, Beis Hillel omrim kol halaylah
shelah, she could multiple times you can have sex that night and
you assume it's all hymenal bleeding. But after that night any blood
is considered נדה. niddah. נותנים לה עונה שלימה. Nosnim lah onah sheleimah.
She has a full עונה, onah, full period. So we've discussed before
עונה onah as either
a day an entire day time period or a night time period.
Let's this is the גמרא'ס Gemara's now question: in this context what
does עונה onah mean, that during the period this
period she can assume that the bleeding is hymenal? So the גמרא
Gemara says, וכמה עונה שלימה?
v'kamah onah sheleimah? What is a full period? פירש רבי אמי לילה
וחצי יום. Pirish Rabbi Ami laylah vachatzi yom. The night and even
half into the day. Again see Rachel you're here yesterday, we also
spoke about sex during the day, which the גמרא Gemara problematized sometimes.
Sometimes the גמרא Gemara problematizes sex during the day, sometimes not. Anyway,
so here the any bleeding during sex or maybe even after the
sex act, it's a little bit unclear, but anyway for the night
and the day, she can assume is half the day, hymenal bleeding.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ומי בעינן כולי האי? u'mi ba'inan kulei
hai? Do we need that much? Actually, "need" is a little bit
funny, it means do we allow that much? Right, anyway. ורמינהי, U'reminhi,
I'll ask you on this whether עונה onah refers to a whole
day and a half. Not a day, like a night and a
half. Normally you assume it's either night or day. They just כל
הלילה כולו, kol halaylah kulo, they're saying it means more than that?
Yeah. Okay, so let's yeah, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says about this. הרי שהיו גיתו ובית בדו טמאים. Harei she'hayu gito
u'veis bado tmei'im. Now we have something that's completely irrelevant except to
I mean or seems irrelevant, completely off topic except for it's going
to discuss an עונה. onah. הרי שהיו גיתו ובית בדו טמאים, Harei
she'hayu gito u'veis bado tmei'im, a person's wine vats or olive presses
were טמא. tamei. He was used to be an עם הארץ am
ha'aretz and wasn't careful about טומאה, tumah, or something טמא tamei touched
them and now ובקש לעשותן בטהרה. u'bikeish la'asosan b'taharah. You want to
clean it out and make all future wine or oil, you want
to say you know what they buy oil, right, it's like virgin
what is it like what?
Extra virgin! So here you want to make it real pure, real
pure, it says טהור. tahor. Okay, so you want to make it
real pure. Anyway, so now you gotta get rid of all the
old stuff that's טמא. tamei. You gotta dry it out, all that
other liquid is טמא, tamei, it's gonna make טמא tamei the new
stuff. How do you clean it out so that you can start
afresh? כיצד הוא עושה? Keitzad hu oseh? What do you do? הדפין
והלולבים והעדשים, Hadafin v'halulavim v'ha'adashim,
the boards which is what you use to press down on the
stuff, right, and the like brooms, and the עדשים adashim which is
the actual sort of vat itself, מדיחן, madichan, those you have to
rinse out. Okay, do a good rinse because all of this stuff,
by the way, these are interesting questions because these are things that
absorbed in cold. Things absorb in heat. So it's not like you
have to do הגעלה, hagalah, you know, like kashering כלים, keilim, but
you have to get all the liquids out. So that stuff you
rinse. העקלים של נצרים ha-akalim shel netzarim
and like sort of the wickers of made out of either נצרים,
netzarim, which is like hemp, ושל בצבוץ veshel bitzbutz
or canvas. נצרים netzarim is more
what's that stuff that they make those like what's it called wicker
baskets, you know, those like woven stuff like they make the אתרוג
etrog sort of accordion things out of it. That wicker, is that
what it's called?
Anyway, wicker or hemp, anyway, those types of things which are not
so absorbent, those מנגבן, menagvan, you don't have to rinse, you don't
have to wash them out, it's enough to dry them off. שופא
ושל גמי, shifa veshel gami, things that are made out of שופא
shifa and גמי gami which I know, some different types of material,
I don't know, what is גמי, gami, yeah,
although does that... yes, some type of a what, yeah, now it's
I don't know we call rubber but something like that. Yeah, what
does he give, does he say what these are? Whatever. Some type
of more absorbent material. So those, even rinsing and wiping is not
enough. So what do you have to do? מישנן. meyashnan. You have
to let them get old so that any of the liquids absorbed
in them sort of get, you know, come out over a period
of
time. וכמה מישנן? ve-kamah meyashnan? How old you have to let them
get in order to assume that they got rid of their liquid?
י"ב חודש, yod bet chodesh, 12 months. I should say that, by
the way, this is important because for some פוסקים poskim this is
used as a model for things that you can't kasher, for example,
like the whole China and pottery question. That maybe we can assume
that after 12 months everything's just somehow dried up and come out
and so on. Now, this is an issue where it's got absorbed
in cold. You know, the pottery question is a question, the China
question is a question more about absorbed in hot.
But even hanging on the hot sun for like a month, that's
not enough?
I don't know, what can I say? רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel אומר omer מניחן manichan מגת לגת, migat legat,
not 12 months, but from one pressing to the next pressing, ומבד
לבד u-mibad lebad
from one wine press to the next or from one olive press
to the next. So מה איכא בינייהו? mah eika beinaihu? So what,
from one to the next is a year? That's the same thing
about a year, and so what, what do you mean? I mean,
the period of pressing takes a few months, so if you just
do the gap between, it's a lot less than
a year. But for some reason the גמרא Gemara assumed that he
meant from like the beginning of one period to the beginning of
the next. So if that's true, that is the same as a
year. So the גמרא Gemara says no, איכא בינייהו חרפי ואפלי. eika
beinaihu charfei ve-aflei.
Let's say it's a month where the next harvest is either early
or late. So if you go from the beginning of one harvest
to the next, it won't necessarily be a year. Sometimes it'll be
more, sometimes it'll be less. Okay. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yosi omer
הרוצה לטהר מיד, ha-rotzeh letaher mi-yad, if you don't want to wait
the year, how do you deal with these absorbent things? מגעילן ברותחין.
magilan berotchin. So then you do like you do when you're kashering
your, you know, pots. You put them in boiling hot water. Okay.
או חולטן במי זיתים o choltan be-mei zeitim or you scald them
in olive water. It's not oil, and presumably it's more like the
water that comes out before like the actual olive oil comes out.
Anyway, you scald them or you or you do הגעלה, hagalah, you
boil them in hot water. And therefore you take care of it.
So by the way, the interesting thing is, look, something that you
would do הגעלה hagalah on, the alternative is 12 months. Now, admittedly,
this is stuff that absorbed by cold, but you can understand why
that allows some פוסקים poskim to say, oh, so if you can't
do הגעלה hagalah like pottery or whatever, maybe the 12 months is
a way of working. Anyway, that's interesting in terms of how, where
this actually has a practical implication. Yeah, I don't know what's special
about olive water. All that other stuff. If you forget something. Right.
So we'll have it stored away. Right. All year. Right. The problem
is that then like the גמרא, Gemara, you have an eight-day difference
depending on how long the year was, right, because it's the last
day of פסח Pesach to the first day of the next. Anyway,
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel אומר omer משום mishum
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi מניחן תחת הצינור שמימיו מקלחין. manichan tachat ha-tzinor
she-meimav me-kalchin. You could put it under running water. Running water will
do better than just sort of like rinsing it in water. That
like constant, you know, pressure will get out
some of the absorbed stuff. Oh, so either a pipe
which has running water, או במעין שמימיו מרובין o be-mayan she-meimav merubin
or some type of a
wellspring that has rushing water. וכמה, ve-kamah, how long do you have
to leave it under running water? This is why we're calling the
whole thing עונה, onah, for an עונה. onah. So now we're going
to discuss what that עונה onah is. כדרך שאמרו ביין נסך כך
אמרו בטהרות. kederech she-amru be-yayin nesech kach amru be-taharot. The same way
this is how you kasher things for יין נסך, yayin nesech, meaning
let's say you have a vat, a wine vat that was used
by a non-Jew and you now want to start making kosher wine
in it. So how would you kasher the wine vat? Same way,
you'd have to get out all of the absorbed wine liquid that's
been absorbed in cold. So the same way you would kasher something
for יין נסך, yayin nesech, you'd kasher it here for טהרות. taharot.
כך אמרו בטהרות. kach amru be-taharot. So the גמרא Gemara just says
כלפי לייא? klapi laya? What? The opposite makes sense. בטהרות שנינו. be-taharot
shaninu. We have just, we've never said something similar to יין נסך.
yayin nesech. We're talking here about טהרות. taharot. אלא, ela, fine, reverse
it. כדרך שאמרו בטהרות, kederech she-amru be-taharot, like we are saying now
by טהרות, taharot, כך אמרו ביין נסך kach amru be-yayin nesech is
a similar requirement by יין נסך, yayin nesech, right? Because here it's
sort of assuming that there isn't a background where we said something
similar by יין נסך. yayin nesech. So okay, the same way by
טהרות, taharot, this is how you kasher your wine vat and your
olive press. If you wanted to kasher your wine vat to make
real kosher wine in the sense of... it was getting out of
having been processed by non-Jews, you'd כשר kasher it the same way.
But now we get to our statement about עונה. Onah. וכמה עונה
Ve-kamma Onah and how much is this עונה Onah of running it
under, putting it under running water? אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan או יום
או לילה o yom o layla either a day or a night,
which is normally what we say an עונה Onah is. Rabbi Chana
so now we've got a problem. Right? Exactly. Or not a day
and or not a night and a half a day, which is
the Gemara's question. Rabbi Chana Shuna ve-amre leh Rabbi Chana bar Shuna
de-Rabbi Chana Shuna or the son of Shuna, אמר רבה בר בר
חנה אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan
says in the name of Rabbah bar bar Chana in the name
of Rabbi Yochanan, חצי יום וחצי לילה. chatzi yom ve-chatzi layla. No,
not a full day or a full night, half a day plus
half a night. ואמר רב שמואל בר יצחק ולא פליגי, Ve-amar Rav
Shmuel bar Yitzchak ve-lo peligi, they're really not debating. הא בתקופת ניסן
ותשרי הא בתקופת תמוז וטבת. Ha bi-tekufas Nissan ve-Tishrei ha bi-tekufas Tammuz
ve-Teves. They're both trying to say 12 hours. The problem is, is
a daytime 12 hours? Well, it depends what time of the year.
If it's בתקופת ניסן ותשרי, bi-tekufas Nissan ve-Tishrei, spring or fall, so
then the days are roughly even, the day and night is roughly
even, especially if it's right near the equinox. So in those times,
you could say all of the daytime, all of the nighttime, you're
basically saying 12 hours. However, בתקופת תמוז וטבת, bi-tekufas Tammuz ve-Teves, if
you're talking about summer or winter, so obviously daytime or nighttime is
either going to be a lot less than 12 hours or a
lot more than 12 hours. So what would define 12 hours? Half
the day and half the night. That's right, because if you have
a day that's 14 hours long and a night that's 10 hours,
half the day is 7 and half the night is 5, that
gets you 12. Obviously. So that's two ways of saying 12 hours
depends what time of year you're talking about. It does. But that's
the implicit point here of the Gemara. Okay, so if it says
12 hours I'd suppose. Anyway, all right. So anyway, here's the problem.
Here we say it's an עונה, Onah, 12 hours. We don't say
a night plus half a day. How come by בית הלל Beis
Hillel statement are we saying a night plus half a day? So
the Gemara says: Okay, הכי נמי נימא גבי נדה חצי יום וחצי
לילה. Hacha nami neima gabei nidda chatzi yom ve-chatzi layla. All right,
so we didn't mean a night and a half a day. We
meant half a night and half a day. So the Gemara says:
אה לילה וחצי יום גמרת, Aha layla ve-chatzi yom gamrat, but you
didn't say that. You said a night and half a day. So
אלא אי לילה דניסן ותשרי אי חצי יום וחצי לילה דטבת ותמוז.
Ela i-layla de-Nissan ve-Tishrei i-chatzi yom ve-chatzi layla de-Teves ve-Tammuz. So okay,
it doesn't mean a night and a half a day. It means
either it means either a לילה layla if we're talking about like
spring or fall or night and half a day, חצי לילה חצי
יום. chatzi layla chatzi yom. So somehow it got conflated. It said
לילה layla or חצי לילה חצי יום chatzi layla chatzi yom and
that got conflated to לילה וחצי יום. layla ve-chatzi yom. But we
were really saying 12 hours. Okay, that's one answer. Still sticking that
we're saying the same thing. ואיבעית אימא שאני כתובה דמשי בה טובא
Ve-iba'is eima shani kesuva de-mashi bah tuvei that when you're dealing with
a כתובה kesuva there's a lot of going over of the details.
What happens to, where were we talking about כתובה? kesuva? Because remember
we're talking about them having sex the night, the wedding night, right?
And therefore and they're having sex, they can have it the whole
night and they can assume it's Haimen blood. So the point is
you don't always get to be alone the חתן chosson and כלה
kallah first thing of the night. I mean they didn't say that
the band is playing and you have to work it all the
details with the caterer or whatever after the wedding. Though they're saying
that there's sometimes the wedding you're supposed to get married on Wednesday
but sometimes the details shlep on until the middle of Wednesday night
because there's a lot of negotiating around the כתובה, kesuva, this is
when the כתובה kesuva was a real document, a real how much
is the חתן chosson promising and committing and so on. So therefore
sometimes these things shlep on and they don't get to be alone
until the middle of the night. So when we said night and
half the day we really meant 12 hours. We're just assuming that
the חתן chosson and כלה kallah aren't alone don't have opportunity to
have sex until the middle of the night anyway. So therefore night
and half a day means half the night and half the day.
So in the end we are saying 12 hours in one way
or another, that's what we mean. Okay, now we get to the
major shift where we talk about nowadays because until now basically the
Haimen bleeding was a way of assuming whether it was for the
whole night whether it was at least for the first act of
sex four nights whatever it was that it was not menstrual bleeding.
Now we're going to introduce a major shift. Let's take a look.
רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav ve-Shmuel de-amri tarvaihu, Rav and Shmuel both
say, הלכה, halacha, the הלכה halacha is, בועל בעילת מצוה ופורש. bo'el
beilas mitzvah u-poresh. You have sex the first time and then you
separate. Right. Presumably regardless of the circumstances. Yes, yes, regardless of the
circumstances. Now how is that different than what we've been saying? One
way is what Michael's saying, we don't make a difference of four
nights, עד שתחיה מכה, ad she-tichyeh makka, we just say once period.
Okay, but at least the Gemara did have that scenario by a
בוגרת שראתה bogeret she-ra'asa which is thankfully our cases nowadays, a woman
that's already mature and that has had her period that it did
also said okay they have the first act of sex. But what's
so fine? They have the first act of sex bleeding isn't a
problem and then they assume any bleeding afterwards will be a problem.
So you could have read Rav and Shmuel like that that they're
saying okay everybody we'd make לא פלוג lo pelug everybody is once
and But the thing that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* picks up on
is the extra word that they add of ופורש *u'poresh*. Until now
we said אין לה אלא ביאת מצוה בלבד *ein lah ela bi'as
mitzvah bilvad*, that they can only attribute it for the first act
of sex. Here it says separate immediately. Why are you separating? Until
now we said the first act of sex isn't a problem if
there's bleeding afterwards it's a problem. By saying separate, it's suggesting that
you treat even the bleeding of the first act of sex to
be a problem and you're not going to have sex afterwards. So
this becomes the shift of rather than attributing bleeding to hymenal bleeding
at least once, we say that any hymenal bleeding we're going to
treat it as if it's נדה Niddah *niddah* bleeding and therefore after
the first act of sex they have to separate regardless. Okay, well
we'll talk about it in a minute, but let's first sort of
see that that is the major shift, not just a little plug
that everybody only gets one once, but that even that once is
considered to be a problem afterwards you separate. So let's take a
look. מתיב רב חסדא *Mativ Rav Chisda*. So רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*
asked them this. מתיב ונתנה לו רבי ארבעה לילות מתוך שנים עשר
חודש *Mativ v'nasna lo Rebbe arba leilos mitoch yud-beis chodesh*. He gets
at a ברייתא *braisa* that you had four times over a year,
it's not just once and then you separate. So אמר ליה רבה
*amar leh Raba*, הדור אפירכא למה לי *hadar u-pircha lamah li*? Why
are you looking for ways of asking questions? Oh, you have to
run over to look at רבי *Rebbe*. How about איכא דמתיב *eika
d'masiv* the whole משנה *Mishnah* is against what they just said? Right?
Whole משנה *Mishnah* says four nights, this, that, and anyway it doesn't
say פורש *poresh*. So who סבר מעשה רב *sevar ma'aseh rav*? Now
he wanted to prove that it wasn't just a theoretical ruling in
the משנה *Mishnah*, he wanted to prove from what רבי *Rebbe* did
that we actually have paskened like that in practice. Look in practice
we rule like this משנה *Mishnah*. What are you guys doing, you
know, rejecting the whole משנה *Mishnah*? So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מכל
מקום רב ושמואל קשיא *mi-kol makom Rav u'Shmuel kashya*. Okay, so now
we got a problem. He's going against the משנה *Mishnah*, he's going
against practice of רבי *Rebbe*. What are they doing? So the גמרא
*Gemara* says אינהו דעבדי כרבותינו *inhu de-avdi k'raboseinu*. They are ruling like
a different opinion. רבותינו *raboseinu*, our rabbis. דתניא *d'tanya*, we taught in
a ברייתא *braisa*, רבותינו חזרו ונמנו *raboseinu chazru v'nimnu*. After that whole
משנה *Mishnah*, the rabbis got together again and took a vote. And
they said בוא ביאת מצוה ופורש *bo bi'as mitzvah u'poresh*. That after
the first act of sex you have to separate. You assume you
treat the bleeding as problematic and even that first time and therefore
you have to separate after. So you're the רב *Rav* said אמר
רב בוגרת נותן לה לילה הראשון *amar Rav bogeres nosen lah lailah
harishon*. I'll get that out of the way in a minute. אמר
עולא *Amar Ulla*. So עולא *Ulla* said כי הוו בה רבי יוחנן
וריש לקיש בתינוקות *ki havu bah Rebbe Yochanan ve-Reish Lakish b'Tinoukes*. When
רבי יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan* and ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* were learning תינוקות
*Tinoukes*, if you look at the top of your page, that's the
name of our מסכת *masechet*. תינוקות *Tinoukes*, right? It's the first word
of the it means the young girl. First word of the משנה
*Mishnah*. When they were learning this פרק *perek*, לא הוו מסקי מינה
אלא כדמסקי תעלא מבי כרבא *lo havu maskei mineh ela k'masik ta'ala
mi-be karda*. This is some type of idiom. They couldn't they wouldn't
bring out from it except what a fox takes out of a
sort of of a plowed field, which means like I guess if
the field is plowed there's no food growing in it, so he
can't he doesn't get anything out of he doesn't reap any fruit,
he just gets dust. So you know they whenever they learned it
they didn't come up with nothing practical they got from it. Because
we don't pasken this entire פרק *perek* is basically what the גמרא
*Gemara* is saying. I mean you have theoretical discussions, but practically nothing
comes out of this because we don't pasken any of this. Why?
ומסיימי בהכי *u-misayemei b'hacha*. Would conclude בוא ביאת מצוה ופורש *bo bi'as
mitzvah u'poresh*. That basically forget the whole פרק *perek*, have sex the
first time and then separate. None of these distinctions. You never attribute.
Hymenal bleeding is never a way of getting out of a problem,
actually it's a reason for treating it as a type of דם
נדה Niddah *dam niddah* and you just separate. One more line. What?
You don't see? No, presumably if you do see blood. I'll talk
about all those things, let me read one more line and then
I'll take a step back and talk about this. אמר ליה רב
אבא לרב אשי *amar leh Rav Abba l'Rav Ashi*. So רב אבא
*Rav Abba* said to רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, אלא מעתה בעל נפש
Ba'al Nefesh, לא יגמור ביאתו *ela mei-ata ba'al nefesh lo yigmor bi'aso*.
Oh, well if that's true, so then I mean first time couples
having sex imagine this. I mean tough enough right now as it
is on the wedding night. First time they have sex and then
they have to separate and then she's a נדה *niddah* and then
they can't you know and they have to be separate for another
like you know 11, 12 days. Anyway so it says well maybe
as soon as you're beginning the act of sex there's a little
blood you can't even complete the act, don't even fully penetrate because
if you're treating the blood as נדה *niddah* bleeding. So it says
אם כן לבו נוקפו ופורש *im kein libo nokfo v'poresh*. Now if
that's true then his heart will sort of pound and it'll trouble
him and he'll separate. I mean you're telling him to separate anyway.
Okay but the point is that I mean that's not reasonable. Anyway
what are you going to do then every time they're going to
every time they're going to exactly. So you have to at least
allow them. Even if you don't think it's a problem, you know
the first the wedding night, yeah. No it is a problem in
the חרדי *charedi* community. What what consummating the act of sex the
wedding night? Yes, but I never realized that it was prob that
it might also have to do with right. So well they're right
I mean the very fact that the first night is going to
be just one act and then separate you know puts a lot
of you know makes it very difficult. And then also means that
if they're having a hard time getting the mechanics down and then
there's you know and there's a partial penetration and a little bleeding
or whatever then they have to stop. You know. And it's a
very challenging it's tremendously challenging. Well why would they So let me
say something about what this is about. First of all okay the
question is how much is this הלכה Halakhah *halacha*, you know there's
no logic for it like it's clear that the logic is that
this is דם מכה Dam Makkah, *dam makah* it's bleeding based on
the hymen it's not דם נדה *dam niddah*. Right, and the תוספות
*Tosafot* there say that they don't want to rule like רב *Rav*,
so תוספות *Tosafot* says, even if he was ruling like רב *Rav*
correctly, תוספות *Tosafot* says, even if he was ruling like רב *Rav*
correctly, רב *Rav* here says that they don't have the first, you
know, that they can't attribute it. So okay, okay, okay, so רב
*Rav* that one the תוספות *Tosafot* didn't take because at least there
it would be consistent with this משנה *Mishnah*. And what רב *Rav*
and שמואל *Shmuel* are saying on this עמוד ב' *Amud Bet* is
going sort of, you know, being more מחמיר Machmir, *machmir* than the
משנה *Mishnah*. And it basically is assumed that this approach is really
just sort of a חומרא *chumra*, I mean, and you know, although
it says like רבותינו חזרו ונמנו *Rabboteinu Chazru VeNimnu*, it's like there's
a consensus of ruling, but we actually have very strong evidence that
from the period even after רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel* were early
in the אמורא *Amora* period, but we have evidence that even well
into the Geonic period there was differences of practices about how much
to treat that hymenal bleeding as problematic or not as if it
were דם נידה *dam niddah*, and it took a while really through
the Geonic period for that to consolidate and to say דם בתולים
Dam Betulim, *dam betulim* is treated as דם נידה *dam niddah*, and
it certainly is a sort of a stringency on top of what
the real הלכה *halacha* is in the you know should be in
the משנה *Mishnah* based on the fact that we know that it's
not menstrual bleeding, at least the first time it's hymenal bleeding. Just
one second. So what is it about? So it's never exactly clear
what motivated it. It does seem to fit into a principle we're
going to see, it's fascinating, we have like a week left of
מסכת נידה *Masechet Niddah*, and we have yet to see probably the
most important line of מסכת נידה *Masechet Niddah*, which is the statement
about about רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* that בנות ישראל החמירו עצמן *Benot
Yisrael Hechmiru Atzman* that women started treating even a tiny drop of
blood every as if they were a נידה *niddah*. Right? תוספתא *Tosefta*?
I think so. Yeah, yes it is. Anyway, so and not as
a נידה *niddah* also, that is, as if it made them a
זבה *zavah* and they had seven clean days and all of that.
That began a process of being extremely strict, of basically saying even
the smallest drop of blood you put all the stringencies on it,
we assume it's a זבה *zavah* and seven clean days and the
whole thing. So there is one way of understanding it, the רמב"ם
*Rambam* sort of frames it this way, that this is like an
attitude within that this is an approach that's within that same spirit,
that we're just מחמיר Machmir *machmir* on everything. So in the same
way we say that a little drop of blood you treat as
a זבה *zavah* and seven days, even though it's really only a
נידה *niddah* and so on, seven clean days, we're also going to
say that any blood, even if it's hymenal blood, we're going to
treat it as if it's נידה *niddah* blood, it's all a type
of a big we don't make distinctions, we're just מחמיר *machmir* across
the board. רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira*. And right, and that's probably where
it's coming from, although the the timing doesn't work, רבי זירא *Rabbi
Zeira* is much later, but who you know רב *Rav* and שמואל
*Shmuel* were very early, but clearly there's just this some sense of
like we're not going to play around with all these distinctions, we're
just going to be across the board. Of course the simpler across
the board would be to say okay, you're off the first time
of sex, afterwards it's a problem. Why you add to that of
treating hymenal blood as נידה *niddah* blood is not really clear, it's
clearly coming from a general movement to just be much more strict
about any bleeding. Now I will say an interesting thing though, which
is the רמב"ן Ramban *Ramban* draws a conclusion from this which is
radical, and thank God we don't פוסקן *pasken* like that. The רמב"ן
*Ramban* says look, we know that this is not hymenal blood, not
menstrual bleeding, it's hymeno, it's מכה *makah* essentially a wound and we're
still strict, so the רמב"ן *Ramban* says oh so that indicates that
now we're going to treat any blood even מכה *makah* blood as
נידה *niddah* blood, so even when you know it's a מכה *makah*
and all of the other ראשונים *Rishonim* say oh no absolutely not,
no indication about that, that would be crazy I mean obviously the
implications about that would be would be like horrific, so they say
no no no the reason the rabbis were able to be strict
here was because it was only once, because you know this is
דם בתולים *dam betulim* everybody has it, it's only once, and therefore
we can be strict here and treat it as נידה *niddah* blood,
but that's not going to be with מכה *makah* which could be
persistent and could be ongoing and could be other types of issues.
What would be the reason? So again it's not a clear reason
other than just a downside and very little upside. Right. I mean
the other thing that gets mentioned is that the גמרא *Gemara* has
before said that it seems that when a women get sexually excited
דם חימוד *dam chimmud* which might cause them to have some bleeding,
some uterine bleeding. So some want to say something similar that either
the sort of the trauma of the having the hymen ruptured on
that first act of sex and or combined with or whatever that
sexual excitement maybe that leads to a certain amount of uterine bleeding,
not hymenal bleeding, and it gets mixed up with the blood of
the hymen and therefore we have to be strict, so it's a
fear of contamination. Yeah but these reasons are very far from convincing.
All of a sudden we're worried that now this hymenal bleeding has
some menstrual bleeding mixed up in it and so on, it really
seems that it's being strongly propelled by the general stringencies that begin
to grow up around נידה *niddah*, which is beyond all of the
הלכה *halacha* we've been learning, we start doing big לא פלוג *lo
plug*, just treat everything the same. and so on, with at least
here, thankfully, we're not going as far as the רמב"ן, that we
don't have a whole category of דם מכה, but at least this
thing which is limited to once, that at least we do say.
So and that does lead to tremendous, like you said, challenges in
terms of the wedding night that they haven't had sex before, you
know, they haven't even been physically intimate if they're keeping הלכה as
they should and then they have sex and then they have to
separate and then they can't, you know, and they have to wait
another twelve days. So it, and going back to James's question, all
of this presumably is when there is some blood, but because the
גמרא just says בועל בעילת מצוה ופורש, Boel Beilat Mitzvah U'Poresh, the
practice develops that after the first act of sex even if there
was no blood seen, yeah, after they've had sex once, full penetration,
they separate regardless. Interesting, right? According, well, yeah, but we're thankfully not
dealing with that. Yeah. This phrase though, בעל נפש, Ba'al Nefesh, I
think is really hinting at a taboo. If the guy is sensitive,
a בעל נפש, Ba'al Nefesh, then he'll be so repulsed, he'll withdraw
right away. Yeah, though בעל נפש, Ba'al Nefesh I mean... but בעל
נפש Ba'al Nefesh is someone who's very sensitive. Yeah, but בעל נפש
Ba'al Nefesh normally means sensitive in the sense of religiously, religiously very
sensitive, wants to be very careful of not doing anything wrong. And
not psychological? Yeah, but בעל נפש Ba'al Nefesh is not psychological, no.
Yeah, but בעל נפש Ba'al Nefesh, is not used in an aesthetic
way. בעל נפש, Ba'al Nefesh if you look at it, is used
about somebody that's basically מחמיר, wants to be strict about everything, you
know, concerned about transgression. That's what בעל נפש is. But it's a
positive thing, right? Right, but here the גמרא acknowledges that it would
be misplaced. Okay? Here it acknowledges that it would be misplaced. Let
me just say one last thing. No, we're... I know, but if
he were to do it, it would be misplaced here, it would
be פרישות, Perishut, and we don't want him to act that way.
I'll say one last thing about the דם בתולים, so on the
one hand, again, where it came from is not clear. It took
a while to sort of consolidate that approach. It again is probably
propelled by what we're going to learn tomorrow about greater stringencies by
blood across the board, and thankfully here at least it's limited to
it's limited to, like I said, the one night. But it establishes
the entire tone for everything. I know, it's extremely... I understand. Given,
it creates enormous challenges on the wedding night because you're right, the
time when finally they're having a chance to be physically intimate and
together, it has to become a getting together and then separating and
it could be enormously... Depressing? I know, it can be enormously... Let
me say at least one thing. So first of all, what makes
it even more challenging is the, I mean, not more, but mostly
there will be bleeding. Is, you know, what James said is correct,
it gets another stringency on that which is if it's full penetration
then even if there's no blood that is seen. The other interesting
thing is what it means בועל בעילת מצוה ופורש, Boel Beilat Mitzvah
U'Poresh, which at least we translate to mean that until the, you
know, the man has fully withdrawn, then at least they don't have
to worry about it until that time. There's an extreme position of
the ראב"ד Ra'avad that the ראב"ד Ra'avad basically says after full penetration
basically he has to withdraw immediately. Like it's not just after he
withdraws they can't continue to have sex, but he has to withdraw
immediately after full penetration. Isn't that against איסור נדה Issur Niddah that
you're supposed to stay... עמוסה אבר? Amusah Evar? He also said he
has to do that, that's going into that detail. Okay, so anyway,
so there are ways it could be more strict. It could've gone
the רמב"ן's's way and the ראב"ד's's Ra'avad way, but it's pretty strict
as it is and it does create real enormous challenges. Yeah. It's
interesting about this that we're no longer concerned about טומאה. Tumah. Like
you would expect the other way around, that in the time we
were concerned about טומאה Tumah then you'd be more stringent, but then
it ceased to be a concern so it's... That's a good point.
That's a good point that all, I hadn't thought about it that
way, but you're right, that until now all of the חומרות Chumrot
we've been learning, it's clearly been much, much more מחמיר in a
world of טומאה וטהרה. Tumah V'Taharah. We actually said that the issues
around the husband and sex and whatever have been more relatively more
lenient. And now we're seeing that personally when you're focused on the
nowadays, some חומרות Chumrot are, these profound חומרות Chumrot are introduced which
you've never heard about in the world of טומאה וטהרה. Tumah V'Taharah.
It's a very good point. Yeah, what I learned in my חתן
Chatan class and I remember this very clearly is sort of like
almost like a don't ask don't tell policy, that if you don't,
like, you know, do what you need to do, but then don't
look, and if you don't see any blood, you can have as
long as you want. What, after the husband and wife separate? Absolutely.
That is completely wrong. Very personally, from the Upper West Side. No,
we will talk about that afterwards. I cannot believe that for a
minute. What? He said that after the, and when? He said just
for the first night? He said, well certainly you don't, if there's
no blood you're not considered a נדה and you know you don't
have to, it's not like she's a נדה and you can't be
with your wife again. What? All right, we will have to talk
about that. That is, I've heard very clearly... alright we will have
to talk about that, that is, he said after full penetration if
you don't see blood you can Keep on having sex throughout the
night? Yeah. Okay, I'd like to, I will, I will. That was
eleven years ago. Would you do me a favor? Do you still
have contact with him? Okay, I am completely shocked. I will, I
will, I think you might have misunderstood or misremembered, but I will.
Anyway, all right, anyway, so that's a say. So we, so we
will end with this now, we will continue, yeah, we will continue.